

Profile .

I specialize in software engineering and data analysis for neuroscience research. This involves using and developing tools in **machine learning**, **statistics**, and **DSP**. For my daily job, I use **Python**, **MATLAB**, **Latex**, and **Bash** with occasional usage of **C/C++** and **Java**. I have 9 years of software development experience. For the last 5 years, I've been using **Python**.

Experience _

Artificial Intelligence Research Institute (AIRI)

Moscow, Russia Feb. 2022 - Present

RESEARCH FELLOW

• Developing online timeseries analysis pipeline in **Python**

• Building machine learning model for timeseries prediction

Higher School of Economics, Centre for Cognition and Decision Making

Moscow, Russia

JUNIOR RESEARCH FELLOW

Feb. 2017 - Dec. 2021

- Developed an analysis pipeline in Python, ("metacognition" on github), supervised 2 students on using it
- Led 4-people group developing software for real-time feature extraction and 3D visualization of brain activity from EEG in Python
- Open-source contribution. Sped up by a factor of 10 a core data-processing routine in MNE-python by vectorizing the algorithm
- Administered a laboratory GPU cluster running **Linux**
- Developed and taught a course "MATLAB for data analysis" to undergraduate psychology students

University of Montreal, CERNEC lab.

Montreal, Canada

VISITING RESEARCHER, TEMPORARY POSITION

Oct. - Dec. 2015, May 2016 - Dec. 2016

- Preprocessed MEG dataset of 90 subjects for classification using **Python** scripts
- · Built a classifier for ASD patients vs. Controls with 75% accuracy using classical ML and information geometry in Python
- · Co-developed an open-source Python package for heavy neuroimaging data processing, Neuropycon, Meunier et al. [2020]

Moscow State University for Pedagogics and Education, MEG Center

Moscow, Russia

JUNIOR RESEARCH FELLOW

Feb. 2015 - Dec. 2018

• Published two papers in international collaboration with the University of Montreal, see Alamian et al. [2017a,b]

Scientific Research Institute of System Analysis

Moscow, Russia

RESEARCH ASSISTANT, PROMOTED TO JUNIOR RESEARCH FELLOW

Jun. 2011 - Jan. 2015

• Tested commercial C++ software for simulations of flow in jet engines by comparing simulated vs. theoretical shock wave parameters

Education

Ph.D. in computer science

Moscow, Russia

HIGHER SCHOOL OF ECONOMICS, FACULTY OF COMPUTER SCIENCE

Jan. 2016 – Nov. 2021

- Thesis: "Optimal methods for functional connectivity estimation in magnetoencephalography."
- Published a paper in a leading neuroscientific journal (see Ossadtchi et al. [2018]) by proposing a method for signal leakage suppression when measuring brain areas interaction from EEG/MEG data. Programmed the algorithm and validation scripts in MATLAB

Specialist degree in mechanics (Masters equivalent)

Moscow, Russia

LOMONOSOV MOSCOW STATE UNIVERSITY, DEPARTMENT OF MECHANICS AND MATHEMATICS

Sep. 2008 - Jun. 2013

• Thesis: "Enhancement and validation of LOGOS software for simulations of the reactive fluid flows."

Online courses

COURSERA, EDX, ETC.

- Algorithms part 1, part 2 by Princeton University on Coursera. Assignments in Java
- CS50's itroduction to computer science by Harvard University on EdX. Topics: C, Python, JavaScript, SQL, HTML, CSS, Flask
- Machine learning by Stanford University on Coursera. Assignments in Octave/MATLAB
- CryptoZombies course on smart contracts in Solidity

Honors & Awards

- Selected together with other 178 people across the university for 2-year Higher School of Economics Academic Scholarship for publishing a paper in a high-impact journal
- 2019 St. Petersburg, Russia

Moscow, Russia

• Selected 1-st out of 5 teams together with 2 teammates in IEEE Brain Data Bank Challenge for building a competitive 2-players drinking game based on brain-computer interface

Side projects _

- Smart garden: automatic watering and computer-vision-based growth analytics in Arduino and Python for home-grown basil, link
- Telegram bot in Python for Preferans cards game sayings, link. Context: while playing preferans, there's a lot of witty ways one can comment on the situation in the game. The bot is an expert in such comments. We use it for fun with friends in the game-related chat.

Conference contributions

TALKS

Samara, Russia International conference "Brain-Computer Interface: Science and Practice" COGNIGRAPH: A REAL-TIME EEG-BASED SOURCE IMAGING SOFTWARE 2019 Comprehensive training "MEG at McGill" Montreal, Canada

MEG resting-state in autism. Approach to analysis.

Int. scientific school "Problems of functional synchronization assessment based on MEG/EEG data" Moscow, Russia 2015

GLOBALLY-OPTIMIZED POWER AND SHIFT INVARIANT IMAGING OF COHERENT SOURCES (GO-PSIICOS)

POSTER PRESENTATIONS

Biomag 2018 Philadelphia, USA OBLIQUE PROJECTION FOR PHASE SHIFT INVARIANT IMAGING OF COHERENT SOURCES 2018 Philadelphia, USA Biomag 2018 NEUROPYCON: A PYTHON PACKAGE FOR EFFICIENT MULTI-MODAL BRAIN NETWORK ANALYSIS **5th Workshop on Optically-Pumped Magnetometers** Freiburg, Switzerland

OPM vs. SQUID ARRAYS IN MEG FUNCTIONAL CONNECTIVITY ESTIMATION

Seoul, South Korea Biomag 2016

POWER AND SHIFT INVARIANT IMAGING OF COHERENT SOURCES BY MEG DATA 2016

San Diego, USA **Brain Connectivity Workshop 2015**

GLOBALLY-OPTIMIZED POWER AND SHIFT INVARIANT IMAGING OF COHERENT SOURCES

Selected publications ____

- 1. D. Meunier, A. Pascarella, D. Altukhov, M. Jas, E. Combrisson, T. Lajnef, D. Bertrand-Dubois, V. Hadid, G. Alamian, J. Alves, F. Barlaam, A.L. Saive, A. Dehgan, and K. Jerbi. NeuroPycon: An open-source python toolbox for fast multi-modal and reproducible brain connectivity pipelines. NeuroImage, 219, 2020
- 2. E. Combrisson, R. Vallat, C. O'Reilly, M. Jas, A. Pascarella, A.L. Saive, T. Thiery, D. Meunier, D. Altukhov, T. Lajnef, P. Ruby, Aymeric G., and K. Jerbi. Visbrain: A multi-purpose GPU-accelerated open-source suite for multimodal brain data visualization. Frontiers in Neuroinformatics, 13:14, 2019
- 3. A. Ossadtchi, D. Altukhov, and K. Jerbi. Phase shift invariant imaging of coherent sources (PSIICOS) from MEG data. NeuroImage, 183, 2018
- 4. Z. Yaple, M. Martinez-Saito, N. Novikov, D. Altukhov, A. Shestakova, and V. Klucharev. Power of feedbackinduced beta oscillations reflect omission of rewards: evidence from an EEG gambling study. Frontiers in Neuroscience, 12, 2018
- 5. G. Alamian, A.S. Hincapié, E. Combrisson, T. Thiery, V. Martel, D. Althukov, and K. Jerbi. Alterations of Intrinsic Brain Connectivity Patterns in Depression and Bipolar Disorders: A Critical Assessment of Magnetoencephalography-Based Evidence. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 8(March):1-17, 2017a
- 6. G. Alamian, A.S. Hincapié, A. Pascarella, T. Thiery, E. Combrisson, A. L. Saive, V. Martel, D. Althukov, F. Haesebaert, and K. Jerbi. Measuring alterations in oscillatory brain networks in schizophrenia with resting-state MEG: State-of-the-art and methodological challenges. Clinical Neurophysiology, 128(9):1719-1736, 2017b

2015